Guide to the Paul Jean Gaston Darrot Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul Jean Gaston Darrot papers
1914-1919
MS 591
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(3 boxes)
A collection of 210 photographs and 100 stereoptican glass slides taken by Darrot during World War I in France.
Darrot, Paul Jean Gaston, 1892-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Anita (Mrs. Paul) Darrot in 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Access to the original glass slides are restricted. Researchers must use digital images in Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database (MADID).
Arrangement
Arranged by topic.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Jean Gaston Darrot was born November 8, 1892, in Paris where his higher education included studies at the Ecole Professionelle d'Art and at the Trocadero Art School. In 1912 he joined the French Army and during World War I served in the infantry, artillery and communications section of the engineers. He was assigned to maintenance of telephone lines under fire and towards the end of the war was severely gassed. The photographs in this collection were probably made while he was in the engineers.
Soon after his discharge in 1919, Darrot left France and came to the United States. In 1922 he began working for Seth Thomas Clock Company in New York. Paul Darrot died in Southbury, Connecticut, on February 14, 1958.
* Information for this biographical sketch was taken from a letter written by Anita Darrot to the Yale University Library circa 1969.
Scope and Contents
A collection of 210 photographs and 100 stereoscopic glass slides taken by Darrot during World War I in France.
Related Materials
War Poster Collection, MS 671. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
World War, 1914-1918; Photoprints; Darrot, Paul Jean Gaston, 1892-1958
- Photographs and slides, Circa 1914-circa 1918
  - Series A (45 photographs)
    - Pictures dealing with artillery (anti-aircraft implacements), bombed-out villages and specific ruins, field kitchens (and supply trains), trench and bunker scenes, French field operations (by soldiers), wartime use of French railroad (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Series B (50 photographs)
    - French countryside scenes—peasants at work, photographs showing activities, horse mounted units, French fighter planes, movement of 75mm gun, wartime cemeteries and burial parties, wartime use of civilian vehicles, military parades (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Series C (45 photographs)
    - Views of French countryside, French supply trains (ammunition, wine, etc.), rest camps—ambulance and other means of transporting wounded to camps, telephone exchanges, installation of barbed wire (and other blockades), trench scenes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Series D (50 photographs)
    - Hospital and staff of Soissons, French vehicles and artillery front-line action shots (1918) and aftermath, parades of French, German, and Allied prisoners, clean-up work in French villages—cleaning up bombed-out buildings and German wreckage left behind (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Series E (15 photographs)
    - French landmarks—famous monuments, French prisoners of war released after armistice (1918), international boundary line—France, Germany, Belgium (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (5 plates) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stereoscopic glass slides of World War I scenes in France
    Scope and Contents
    The slides depict primarily infantry warfare in France during World War 1, 1914-1918, concluding with images of the victory parade at the end of the war and the signing of the Treaty of Versailles by President Woodrow Wilson in 1919. A significant number of images depict American troops and artillery. The slides, measuring 1 3/4 inches by 4 3/4 inches, contain duplicate photographic negatives separated by a strip of clear glass on which a brief description has been handwritten in French, presumably by Darrot. Several slides bear an illegible stamp in red ink, the significance of which is unknown.
    Arrangement
    The slides are arranged in alphabetical order by topic and geographic location based on the French description written on each slide. Some slides are numbered and were presumably used by Darrot after the war as he lectured on his wartime experiences to various groups and organizations. Although the numbers are not sequential, they have been retained with the description of the individual slides.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Glass slides in this collection are too fragile to be used. Researchers must use digital images in Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database (MADID).
    - Argonne, Alerte aux gazs (gas alert) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Argonne, Secteur américain (American sector) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Argonne, Train de matérial américain (American transport train) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Artillerie anglaise dans la Somme (English artillery in the Somme) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Artillerie lourde (heavy artillery) (#14748) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - (illegible).....au défilé de la Victoire (at the victory parade) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Au front, Enterrement militaire (military burial at the Front) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Aviation américaine (American aviation) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Avion ..... (illegible) d'une autre avion (a plane [seen?] from another plane) (#989) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Avion incendie (burning plane) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Avion survolant un camp de prisonniers (plane flying over a prison camp) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Camions chargés de troupes (trucks filled with troops) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Camp américain (American camp) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Canon lourd américain (heavy American canon) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Caronne, Tranchée du Balcon (dugout) (#713) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Carrefour des Trois Jurés (crossroads of the three ......) (#545) (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Château Thierry, Prisonniers (prisoners) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Le Châteaurenault coulé en 1917 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      The Châteaurenault was a protected cruiser of the French Navy. Recommissioned at the outbreak of World War 1, Châteaurenault patrolled the Mediterranean. She was torpedoed by the Germans and sank in December 1917.
    - Chavonne, Construction d'un pont (construction of a bridge) (#A-124) (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Cimetière américain (American cemetery) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Colonne, D'infanterie américaine (American infantry) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Colonne, Tranchée (dugout) (#16/85) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Concert américain (American concert) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Couloir? américain (American corridor?) (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Cuisine de territoriaux (local cuisine) (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Cuisine sur le front américain (cuisine on the American front) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Les cuisiniers (the cooks) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Dardanelles, Débarquement (disembarkment) (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Dormans (#23219) (Box 2, Folder 29)
      A French village that sustained heavy damage.
    - Enterrement d'un soldat noir américain (burial of a black American soldier) (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Eparges, attaque du front, 1915 (attack at the front) (#336) (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Eparges, Relevé des morts, 1915 (removal of the dead) (#90/876) (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Etat major américain (American chief of staff) (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Ferme navarin, Infanterie en reserve (Navarin farm, reserve infantry (#C314, 2 duplicate slides) (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Navarin Farm was a position on the Champagne battlefields where heavy fighting took place in 1915 September. The French troops captured German positions here, suffering great losses.
    - Ferme navarin, Infanterie en reserve (Navarin farm, reserve infantry) (#C314, duplicate slide) (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Fort de Douaumont ...... (illegible) en état de défense (in a state of defense) (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Fort Douaumont was captured by German forces in 1916 February and in October that same year was recaptured by the French.
    - Général Pershing au défilé de la Victoire [1919 juillet 14] (#200) (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Un gros obusier américain (a large American howitzer) (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Guillaume II ...... (illegible) (William II, emperor of Germany) (#116) (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Jaulgonne, Front américain (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - L'heure de la soupe (soup time) (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - L'heure de la soupe (soup time) (not a duplicate) (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Les Italiens au défilé de la Victoire (The Italians at the victory parade) (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Joffre et Millerand sur le front remettent des décorations (Joffre and Millerand at the Front giving out medals) (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Karpathes, observateur autrichien (Carpathos, Austrian observer) (#26448) (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Laonnais, Fort de Laniscourt (fort at Laniscourt) (#31108) (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Léon Gambetta .... la Côté turque ( Léon Gambetta ...... (illegible) la Turkish side) (#170) (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Léon Gambetta, an armoured cruiser, was part of the French fleet based at Malta blockading the Austrian Navy in the Adriatic. On April 27, 1915, she was torpedoed by Austro-Hungarian submarine U-5 under the command of Korvettenkapitän Georg Ludwig Ritter von Trapp, patriarch of the Von Trapp Family Singers. Of the 821 men on board, only 137 survived.
    - Marne, cadavres, 1914 (corpses) (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Marne, Eglise occupée (occupied church) (#296) (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Maroc en colonne (Moroccan soldiers in a column) (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Maroc, Ou enterre les morts (Morocca, Where the dead are buried) (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Marseille, ..... (illegible) Marin boche (Marseille,..... German sailor) (LS601) (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Meuse, Cadavre allemand, 1918 (German corpse) (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Meuse, Cadavre américain, 1918 (American corpse) (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Meuse, Cuisine sous bois, 1918 (cooking under trees) (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Meuse, Front américain (American Front) (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Meuse, Un P. C. américain, 1918 (An American pay clerk?) (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Meuse, Pendant l'avance américain, 1918 (During the American advance) (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Meuse, Transport d'un blessé américain, 1918 (Transport of a wounded American) (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Mont Kemmel, Champ de bataille (B139) (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Mont Kemmel, Champ de bataille (B139) (duplicate) (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Mouilly, Enterrement (burial) (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Mouvement américain à Château Thierry (American movement at Château Thierry) (Box 2, Folder 63)
      The Battle of Château-Thierry was fought From June 3-July 18, 1918, and was one of the first actions of the American Expeditionary Force (AEF) under General John J. "Black Jack" Pershing.
    - Nesles, Cimetière américain (American cemetery) (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Nieuport (Box 2, Folder 65)
      Nieuport, later Nieuport-Delage, was a French airplane company that primarily built racing aircraft before World War I and fighter aircraft during the war.
    - Obusier américain (American howitzer) (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Paris, American Legion parade (1 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 67)
      The American Legion was founded in 1919 by veterans who served in the American Expeditionary Forces (A.E.F.) in France during World War I. Members convened in Paris in March 1919, the same year the organization was chartered by Congress.
    - Paris, American Legion parade (2 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Paris, American Legion parade (3 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Marchers carry a Connecticut banner.
    - Paris, American Legion parade (4 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 70)
      Marchers carry a Tennessee banner.
    - Paris, American Legion parade (5 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Paris, Fêtes de la Victoire, Drapeaux américains (Celebration of the victory, American flags) (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Reims, Chauffeurs annamites (Annamese drivers) (#23293) (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Le repos près des faisceaux (Rest near the stack of weapons) (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Salut de drapeau (Salute the flag) (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Soissons, Soldats américains (American soldiers) (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - [Soixante-quinze] 75th américain en action (U.S. Infantry, 75th regiment?) (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Soldats noirs américains (Black American soldiers) (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Somme, Convois américain (American convoy) (#82) (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Souain, Cadavres de Goumiers (Bodies of Goumiers) (#205) (Box 3, Folder 80)
      Moroccan Goumiers were soldiers who served in auxiliary units attached to the French Army of Africa, between 1908 and 1956.
    - La soupe au camp (meal at camp) (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - St. Nazaire, Arrivée des troupes américains (Arrival of the American troops) (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - St. Rémy, Meuse, Génie américain (American engineering) (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Thann, Alsace (#983) (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Tombe de Quentin Roosevelt (Tomb of Quentin Roosevelt) (#187) (Box 3, Folder 85)
      Quentin Roosevelt was the youngest son of President Theodore Roosevelt. He joined the United States Army Air Service where he became a pursuit pilot during World War I. He died in aerial combat over France on Bastille Day, 1918 July 14.
    - Troupes Gorkas (Gurkhan troops) (#23611) (Box 3, Folder 86)
      More than 200,000 Gurkhas (India) served in the British Army during World War I, arriving in France in 1914.
    - Tyrol, ....... (illegible) autrichienne (.....Austrian) (#107) (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Verdun, ..... (illegible) allemand (..... German) (#127) (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Verdun, Boyau allemand ..... (illegible) (German communication trench) (#845) (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Verdun, Cadavres (#826) (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Verdun, Poste de secours allemand (German aid station) (#108) (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Verdun, Tranchée des Baiönnettes (Bayonet trench) (#102) (Box 3, Folder 92)
      Tranchée des Baionnettes is the oldest memorial on the battle fields at Verdun.
    - Verdun, Voie sacrée (Verdun, sacred way) (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Vichy, .....illegible anglais (#0320) (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - La Victoire, Défilé armée américain (Victory, American army marching) (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Vosges, skieurs allemands (Vosges, German skiers) (#927) (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Wilson rend visite au roi des Belges (Wilson visits the king of the Belgians) (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Wilson signant le Traité de Versailles (Wilson signing the Treaty of Versailles) (#9) (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - ......(illegible) abattu (.....destroyed) (#938) (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Unidentified (Box 3, Folder 100)